爸爸，给我讲个故事吧。
Dad, tell me a story.
那就给你讲讲缅甸吧，
I can tell you about Burma,
这个曾被称作黄金之国的地方。
the time when it was called the Gold Country.
想听吗？
This is a story that you like that?
想听！
Yes!
很久很久以前，有一个美丽的国家，
There was once a beautiful country,
缅甸。
Burma.
那里长满了
Everywhere there was
柚树和紫檀树。
forests of teak and ebony.
那时候，老虎经常在热带雨林出没，
At that time,tigers roamed the jungles
大象也悠闲地漫步在辽阔的大草原上。
and herds of elephants roamed the Great Plains.
这个美丽的国家就像是一颗
It was sapphires as blue as the sky azure
美丽的宝石（原文一堆比喻略去）或是
and rubies even redder than your cheeks.
即使像你这样的小公主，做梦也想象不出来的珠宝。
Jewelry that even a princess like you would not dream.
然后呢？
And then?
其实，这是一个悲伤的故事。
In fact, this is a sad story.
从遥远的异国来的军队
Soldiers came from a far country
抢走和毁灭了这里的一切。
and took of all that was most precious.
从此我们变得很穷很穷。
Thus we have become very poor.
宝贝闺女！
My treasure!
亲爱的，乖乖坐这好吗？
Sit there, my darling.
我得走了，妈妈就在那陪着你。
I gotta go, but mom is there.
仰光 1947
大家好！
Hello!
现在最需要的就是组建一个政府。
What is needed urgently
is to form a government.
没有群众的支持，
Without popular support
我们的政府
our government
就不会有民主上的合法性。
will have no democratic legitimacy.
摆平，闪！
Here we go.
昂山将军他……
General!
昂山素季
Aung San Suu Kyi
Aris先生，
M. Aris,
大夫在等你。
The doctor is waiting to see you.
-Hello,Michael. -你好，我是Michael。
-Hello,how r u?              -你好。
-Please take a seat.         -请坐。
-Thanks.                     -谢谢。
牛津 1998
你还有多少时间
It's always very difficult
很难说。
to predict progresses-something like this.
可能只有5个月
It could be as little as 5 months
最多也就5年。
or as long as 5 years.
得抓紧交待后事了。
Enough time for u to put ur affairs on ur hope.
需要我们通知你爱人来处理后事吗？
Would u like us to arrange for ur wife to come to
collect you?
我爱人？
My wife?
她要能来就好了。
Well,if she could.
她现在在缅甸呢。
Now she lives in Burma.
-Good morning!   -同学们好！
-Good morning!   -老师好！
请大家传阅。
（Aris教授，西藏及喜马拉雅学研究员）
Please pass and see around.
谢谢。
Thank you.
今天我想谈谈
Today I want to talk
不丹人对忠于家庭的
about how the Bhutanese people has always
重视，
place great emphasis on family loyalty,
对邻里关系的重视，
Community...
以及对老人的尊重。
And respect for their elders.
下毛雨啊！
This damn rain!
是啊，下你妹啊。请进。
Yes,coming.
确定是癌了吗？
So, it's definite cancer,yes?
前列腺癌。
Prostate cancer, to be precise.
And did they give u any indications of how long before…？
他们告诉你还有多久了吗？
五个月到五年。
I have five months to five years.
坑爹啊，Michael。
Damn it, Michael.
五年也够做很多事了。
U know,I do achieve a lot in five years.
那Suu怎么办？
And what about Suu?
Truly she want to return to Oxford where she can…
她应该也想回来，这样她就能……
Anthony，you know if she ever left Burma,
Anthony，你要知道一旦她离开缅甸，
他们就不会再让她回去了。
they will never allow her to return.
那你怎么办，Michael？你三年没见她了。
And what about you, Michael?
You have not seen her for three years.
她是你的女人，是娃他娘。
She is your wife.
She is the mother of your children.
唯一可惜的是，她一离开，军政府就小人得意了。
It's only the military would
unfold the red carpet if she wanted to leave and come home.
她绝对不能离开。
She cannot possibly walk away.
已经流了太多的血，失去了太多的生命。
Too much blood has been shed,
too many lives was lost.
上百万人民都以她为寄托。
Millions of people are counting on her.
不管发生什么，Anthony。
Whatever it happens, Anthony
你必须答应我照顾好俺娃。
you must promise me you'll keep an eye for the boys.
当然，你还不放心我吗，你懂的。
Of Course!
You can count on me,100%,you know that.
我懂的。
Yes.
- Hello, darling.   -娃他爹。
- Hello, My angel.  -娃他娘。
书写得怎么样了？
How was the book going?
还早着呢。
Slowly.
闻起来好香啊。
That smells good.
- We'll have Burmese tonight.  -我们今天吃缅甸菜。
- Perfect.                     -我都馋了。
你坏。
Stop it.
起好名了吗？
You've found a title?
好了。
Yes.
我的父亲 （作者：昂山素季）
My Father
by Aung San Suu Kyi
大白话。
Very original.
牛津 1988
暴风雨要来了。
A storm is coming.
爹，娘，俺回来了。
Hi, Mom.Hi,Dad.
今天怎么样？
You have a good day?
不错。
It's OK.
I'm starving.
七点吃晚饭。
The supper in at 7:00.
作业呢？
Do you have homework?
都做完了。
It's all done.
Kim。
Kim.
- Well,Almost.         -差不多快完了。
- go and put then.     -去做吧。
Hi, Alexander.
Alexander.
娘。
Hi, mom.
这里是缅甸，画面上是仰光的街头骚乱。
We were in Burma,
Here is violence on the streets of Rangoon.
上万人集会抗议
Tens of thousands of demonstrators protested
当局对学生的屠杀。
against the massacre of students
by the authorities.
据目击者称，
According to witnesses, hundreds of students
数百名参与在Inya湖的非暴力民主活动
taking part in peacefully demonstrations in
的学生
Inya Lake
被军队近距离射杀。
were killed at close range by soldiers.
其他抗议者承受着剧烈的痛苦。
Many more protesters sustains seriously injuries.
民主人士强烈抗议
The demonstrators demanded the departure of junta
自1962年开始上台的军政府。
who ruled the country with an iron fist
since the coup in 1962.
缅甸政府被认为是现存的
The Burmese government is known
最为专制和神秘的政府之一。
As one of the most repressive and
secrets regions.
但尽管军政府下决心镇压这起事件，
But despite the authorities' determination to crush the uprising,
学生运动还是获得了
it appears that students' movement was rapidly
越来越多的支持。
getting massive popular support.
很高兴听到你的声音，
I'm glad to hear your voice.
你娘现在在中心医院。
Your mother is at the central hospital.
你最好早点来。
You should come quickly.
妈妈得了中风。
My mother had a stroke.
我送你上飞机。
I'll saw you on flight.
学乖，帮你爹干活，知道吗？
Be good,won't u?
Help your dad run the house.
我在那用不了电话。
It will be hard for me to get a phone.
所以如果联系不到我也别担心。
So do not worry before you hear from me.
你什么时候回来？
How long will u come back?
一两周吧。
A week,or maybe two.
好了走吧。
Come on, let's go.
都这时候了。
It's very late.
快点，我们没时间了。
Come on, we do not have time.
我爱你。
I love you.
司机麻烦您快点。
Please, hurry.
- You come from England?   -你是英国来的？
- That's it.               -对。
呆多久？
You stay long?
看需要多久了。
The time it takes.
雷叔！
Uncle Leo!
你还是那么漂亮。
You're still beautiful!
你应该已经听说了，
You know what started it all,
仅仅因为将军觉得
this is because the decision to
9是他的幸运数字
ban any domination ​​that wasn't amount count of 9.
就强制在很多方面使用9进制。
（注：1987年，缅甸废除原大钞，改为
使用新印发的面值为45和90的两种货币，
这导致了1988年的骚乱）
For 9 is his lucky number.
连大学都使用9进制。
The universe is count by 9,
学生纷纷上街。
That's way the students took to the streets.
这一切都只是因为一个2b的迷信。
All this is just because of the superstitions of a madman.
有什么需要我的就给我电话。
Call me if u need me.
一定。谢谢你了，雷叔。
I will. Thank you for everything, Uncle Leo.
热爱祖国。
LIKE THE MOTHERLAND
Suu!
娘。
Mom.
感觉怎么样了？
How do u feel?
有点累。
Tired.
你听说屠杀的事了吗？
Did u hear about the massacre?
听说了，全世界都在看着我们这。
Yes,the riots that followed
made headlines across the world.
娃们还好吗？
How's my little boys doing?
看您，都那么大了还叫娃。
Not so little these days.
该解手了。
It's time to go to the toilet.
麻烦你们了。
Thank you.
快点。
Come & go!
别闹了，好好听老师话啊。
Stop it.
Come on,have a good day.
你也是。
Have a good day!
快点
- Go ahead.
Kim，把领子翻下来。
Kim, put ur collar down.
好。
Yes, that's it.
晚上见。
Goodbye!
她见过什么人吗？
Did she talk to others?
没几个。
Only a few.
她说在这待多久了吗？
Does she said the duration of her stay?
她说想呆多久就带多久。
She said "how long it takes."
好，随时向我汇报。
Return here immediately.
怎么了？
What are you doing?
他们在搜捕学生，我们必须离开。
They are looking for the students.We have to go.
等等，她不能离开这。
Hold on.She can not leave this state.
等会！
Wait!
Don't u think of…？
你想过……？
先冷静好吗。
Calm down first.
先让她躺着，我们下去看看到底出什么事了好吗。
I suggest we take her back to the bed, and then
go down to see what's happening.
救救我！
Help!
我来吧，你去看看其他人。
Help others out there!
打倒独裁！
Our struggle!
放过他们吧！他们都伤得很严重。
Leave them! These are patients.
不要！
Stop!
我代表祖国，代表人民，代表我胸前飘扬的红领巾杀了你。
I wear the red scarf.
I have the right to kill you.
仰光爆发新的暴力事件，
New violence in the Rangoon
游行示威者受到新一轮的报复行动。
where protesters came under bursts of retaliation.
今晨军队向学生开火。
This morning
soldiers opened fire on students
医院人满为患,
Hospital near Rangoon.
The balance sheet is very heavy.
当局再次宵禁。
A new curfew was once again be introduced.
英国大使馆
Embassy of Great Britain
Mikey!
Suu!
娃他娘，你怎么样？
Darling! How are you?
真高兴还能听到你的声音。
So good to hear your voice.
我也是。
You, too.
你没事吧，这两天一直在担心你。
You've managed to dodge bullets?
Despite myself, I was beginning to be worried.
对不起，之前一直脱不开身。
I'm sorry,
I cannot get away until now.
没事的。
Do not worry.
我想你们了。
I miss you all so much.
我们也想你。
We miss you too.
你娘怎么样了？
How's your mother?
大夫说他们也帮不上什么了。
The doctors says that there's nothing more we can do.
所以我准备带她回家。
So I'm going to take her home.
很抱歉。
Oh,I'm sorry,Suu.Of course.Of course.
可这里发生了太多太多，我脑子乱成一团。
But so many other things happening.
I hardly know where to begin.
喂，怎么没声音了。能听见吗？
Hello.I'v lost u.Can u hear me?
又能听见了。
I hear you again.
两个娃还好吗？
Are the boys all right?
都好着呢。
Oh the boys are very fine.
他们都休息了，别担心。
Here they are in bed,
do not worry for them.
告诉Alex，我尽量在他生日前赶回来。
Wishes a Happy Birthday to Alex for me.
放心吧。
Yes.Of course.
我尽量早点回来。
That's I'll catch up for him when I...
争取能赶上。
as Soon as I get home.
一定能赶上的。
Of course, darling.
我们正在办签证。
We try to organize our visas.
希望能早点见到你。
We will join you as soon as possible.
Mikey?
又断线了，网络怎么这么差啊。
Oh goodness, this is useless.
肏。
Slim!
你回来了！没想到还能再次见到你！
You're back! What a joy!
您好！
My My!
都两个孙子了啊？
Two  grandchildren already?
对啊，两个了。
Yes, two grandchildren.
我帮您拿吧。
Give me that.
没事我来吧。你累了吧。我帮你拿回房间。
Leave, you must be tired.
I put it in your room.
狗蛋，快跟上。
Come on, kids.
待在家的感觉真好。
I'm happy to be home.
我也是。
So am I.
昂山女士，
Daw Suu,
我是Nita May。你爱人让我带话。
My name is Nita May.
And u have a message from your husband.
他说他们的签证已经通过了。
He asked me to tell you
they finally got their visas.
他们周末就能过来了。
They will be arriving at the end of the weekend.
谢谢。
Thank you.
有人找你。
Other people came to see you.
一个作家和他的朋友。
A writer and his friends.
你和你爹长得很像。
You look like your father.
不好意思这么早就来打扰。
Sorry for coming so early.
我们刚刚知道您回来了。
We have just learned your arrival
不能放过这个好机会。
and can not pass up the opportunity.
现在是非常时期。
This is a very important period.
我们有很多话要说。
We have so much to discuss.
进来说吧。
Let's start, then.
在这等我。
Wait for me here.
你的鞋。
Your shoes.
这几天
I'm surrounded by bad vibes
我觉得阴风阵阵。
right now.
这不是什么妖魔鬼怪，
None of the 37 spirits.
而是一个孤魂。
It's a ghost.
那
So
是他吗？
it could be him?
就是他。
Yes
本来只有他也掀不起什么风浪，
this is one of the ancestors.
可是，
But
现在他有了帮手，
a spirit came to assist.
一个远道而来的不速之客。
Coming from afar.
是一个女人吗？
A woman?
也许是吧。
Maybe.
要不要让她躲猫猫呢？
Should I remove it?
这样会更危险。
The spirit became ghost
is even more dangerous.
那，
In this case,
还望指点迷津。
how do I get rid of?
一切异象，皆有因果。
If the people are at peace,
国泰民安，妖魔乃遁。
he will not need spirit,
切记切记。
and return it to where it came from.
大仙救命之恩无以为报。
Thank you very much.
只要除了这妖孽，定为大仙重修庙宇再塑金身。
Your advice is always valuable to me.
我就是雷叔。
Leo!
很高兴见到您。
So happy to see you.
很高兴你能来。走吧。
It is good to have u back.
Come on,let's go,please.
娘！
Mom!
我想死你们了。
I missed you.
你最后做好心理准备，这里可是一团乱。
You'd better be prepared for complete chaos.
快点！
Come on!
你好！
Hello!
你好吗？
My My, how are you?
很好。
I'm fine.
很高兴见到你。
Nice to see you again.
- Doctor Aris.    -Aris教授。
- Tom!                -Tom!
- Okay?           -你怎么样？
- You look rang.  -几年没见又帅了嘛。
本来不想过来，
I was on the principle
不过想想Suu一个人在这照顾她母亲。
that  Suu
lived alone to care for her mother.
历史学家很少身临其境真正的历史，享受这一切吧。
Historians rarely see history in motion. Enjoy it.
有什么需要帮忙的，尽管找我。
Please let me help if u need anything.
多谢了。
Thank you very much.
很高兴见到你。
I'm glad you're here.
再往下一点。
Get down down down.
再远一点。
A little further.
好，就放这吧。
Stop.
快过来。
Step away.
他哇哩哇啦什么？
what did he say?
他说
He says
政府会考虑民众的诉求，
that the government can no longer ignore popular discontent,
政府对最近一段时间的动荡
and it assumes its share of responsibility
负有不可推卸的责任。
in the turmoil of recent months.
他自己年龄大了，
And because he's getting old,
也需要休息了。
He will resign.
我们马上会进行一场公投以决定国家的未来走向。
We will have a referendum on the
country's political future.
你好。
Hello.
几个自称来自大学的人想和您谈谈，他们刚说……
Someone from the university want to speak to u.
They said it is...
有急事。
It's urgent.
夫人，我们都是历史系教授。
Madam,my colleagues and I are academics on the history faculty.
我们都相信
And we believe
只有您，才能带领我们走向民主自由的光辉大道。
you are the only person who can lead the country to democracy now.
因为您是昂山将军的女儿，
As the daughter of Aung San,
人民自然都会团结起来追随您的脚步。
the people will automatically unite behind u.
您的父亲为了缅甸的民族独立人民解放奋斗终身。
Your father fight for independence of Burma.
这是完成他遗志的好机会。
Here is an opportunity to finish what he began.
我们必须抓住这个机会。
We must seize this opportunity.
可是我没有一点经验啊。
I'm lack of experience,
你看，
as u can see,
我需要过自己的生活。
I have something to do.
可以再考虑考虑吗？
May I ask you take sometime to consider?
让这些狗消失。
Banish these dogs!
过来。
Come!
将军，大学里的六个教授
General
six professors from the University
告诉昂山素季说人民需要她。
came to tell Aung San Suu Kyi
that the people supported it.
还有呢？
That's it?
他们说要争取民主。
They are fighting for democracy
他们想做别有用心的一小撮人。
they want it to take the lead.
不能任他们乱来了。
It shall not proceed further.
将军英明。
That's it.
好，去吧。
Well, okay.
明天，昂山素季去大金塔。
Tomorrow, Aung San Suu Kyi will go
to Shwedagon.
你的鞋。
Your shoes.
老妖婆，敢玩我。
Bad,minds do not have warned you!
我们已经仁至义尽，但反革命分子的气焰更加嚣张。
Finally,the idea of ​​consulting the people
跟他们没有什么好谈的了。
is not the solution.
是您让谈判的啊。
It was an idea to you.
一时糊涂，
Turns
我也是被蒙蔽了。
I have been badly advised.
登盛将军，
General Sein Lwin ,
给你个任务，
I have a mission to tell you.
制止非法集会，
You will dismantle the centers of opposition
谁敢负隅顽抗，坚决逮捕。
and deter troublemakers.
太多了，抓得过来吗？
There's a lot of people.
监狱有的是地方。
Our prisons are big enough.
眼下最重要的就是
The most important
盯着昂山素季等一小撮人。
is to keep an eye on
Aung San Suu Kyi and her supporters.
将一切不稳定因素消灭在萌芽状态。
Stop any gathering.
- At your orders, sir.  -保证完成任务。
- Okay.                -等你们的好消息。
我们支持你。
We have only respect and admiration for you.
只能走着过去了。
We must continue on foot.
好。
Alright.
走吧。
Let's go.
停车！
Stop the car!
娃们，跟我来。
The boys, come on.
快点。
Hurry.
爹，我们去找点吃的。
Dad, we will look for something to eat.
好，别走太远啊。
Okay, but not too far.
可能有点晚了，
It may be a little late to be seen,
可是我从来没演讲过。
but I've never done public speaking.
不要想太多。
But there is no time to priest!
我们在下面看着你。
We'll be watching from the outside.
尊敬的各位师傅（愿意为和尚），尊敬的父老乡亲。
Reverend monks, the Burmese people!
今天我们共聚一堂，
The purpose of this gathering
就是要让全世界听见这片土地上人民的呼声。
Is to make the world hear
the people's will.
今天我们共聚一堂
The purpose of this gathering today
就是向全世界庄严宣告
is to affirm the desire of the entire country
to be a multiparty democracy.
——我们要将自己的祖国建设成为一个多党制民主国家。
This is what we want to demonstrate.
你们中的一些可能不认识我，
Some of you do not know my story
也想听听
and that's quite normal
我的故事。
to want to know what it is.
因为我一直生活在海外，
Because I have lived abroad
和一个外国人结为夫妻。
and I married a foreigner,
他们就说我不懂缅甸的历史和国情。
they say I do not understand
complex history of the country.
老实说，
Let me honestly say
他们是对的，我在海外生活
that's true.I lived abroad.
也确实嫁给了一个外国人。
And I am also married to a foreigner.
但这都不能阻挡
But this is not provided
我对这片土地无比炽烈的爱，
my love and my devotion to my country
连减轻分毫都不能。
Tampering or mitigated.
我的父亲将自己的一生
My father gave everything he had
献给了缅甸的民族独立和人民解放。
in political life of Burma
并为此付出了自己年轻的生命。
and he paid with his life.
作为他的女儿，
As the daughter of my father,
我不能再对这片土地上发生的一切
I can not remain indifferent
视而不见。
events taking place right now.
现在，前方已经隐隐地浮现出一丝曙光，
The goal we hold so dear
is now in sight.
我们再一次地呼吁让
We call for free elections
规范的民主选举
and regular,
在最短的时间内成为现实。
in the shortest possible time.
母亲！
Mom!
让我们永不分离，
Let us not divide.
联合起来，共同迎接我们的胜利。
Unite forward together towards our goal!
昂山女士！
Daw Suu!
上百万人？
A million people?
可能没这么多。
Maybe not quite a million.
媒体也在？
And the press?
昂山素季,
Aung San Suu Kyi,
昂山将军之女,
the daughter of General Aung San
生活在牛津的一个家庭主妇，两个孩子的母亲，
And until now housewife in Oxford
and mother of two,
成为缅甸走向未来的希望。
became the great hope for the future
in Burma.
难以置信，是吗？
It was incredible.
必须的，不过
Yes, absolutely. However...
罗马不是一夜建成的，
A quarter century
我们也别高兴得太早。
of oppression will not be all done in one day.
革命尚未成功同志仍需努力。
There's still a great deal to do.
这可是Raj的宝贝，在奈温发现以前，你还有点时间。
A pearl of the Raj. It was 80
until Ne Win expelled them.
就这。
Here we are.
漂亮！
Wonderful!
得走了。
You have to go.
我们还有时间。
There is still time.
全国民主联盟
National League for Democracy
- Thank you, Tom.    -谢了，Tom。
- You are welcome.   -应该的。
Kim，怎么了？
What's wrong, Kim?
你已经错过Alex的生日了，
You've missed Alex's birthday,
马上又要错过我的了。
and now you are going to miss mine.
你们留在这太危险了。
It's too dangerous for you to remain here.
如果出什么事怎么办？
I should never forgive myself
if something happens to you.
再说也快开学了，你们不能落下学习。
Anyway.A new term is beginning and u should leave.
为了我
Please...
做一个男子汉好吗？
try to be brave for me.
- Watch over your brother.   -照顾好你弟弟。
- Yes.                       -必须的。
常来信。
I want you to write me every day.
娘，我们走了。
Goodbye, Mom.
- Be strong.    -做个男子汉。
- Do not worry. -必须的。
- I love you.   -我爱你们。
- I love you.   -我们也爱你。
瞧一瞧那个看一看，全国民主联盟需要你们的支持。
The leaflets of the NLD!
各就各位。
Everyone is in place.
全国民主联盟！
National League for Democracy!
我们的第一张大字报。
First Statement
混账！
I understood.
Sein Lwin，你懂的。
Sein Lwin, you know what to do.
请首长放心，保证完成任务。
Yes, Sir.
我们走。
Let's go.
我们必须联合各少数民族，
It must meet all minorities,
但很多民族都藏在大山深处，很难联系。
Myitkjina
but is lost in the mountains.
没有所有人的参与，民主就名不符实。
Democracy will only work if we include everybody.
土匪来了！
They are coming!
别开枪。
Please put your gun down.
我们必须离开。
We should leave.
先把枪放下。
Please put your gun down.
我们不能以暴易暴。
We will not respond in any way
by violence.
Aris教授，你的签证被取消了。
Professor Aris, your visa is canceled.
- You have to come with us to the airport.  -你必须跟我们去机场。
- Do I have time to pack?                -收拾下东西可以吗？
给你一分钟时间。
One minute.
你的签证没有任何问题。
Your program is very full.
家里的事不用担心。
We will have dosed your efforts.
好好照顾好你自己。
Eat and rest well.
我们还会再来的。
We will be back.
上车！
Let's go!
照顾好我娘。
Take good care of Mom.
您放心吧。
Of Course.
再试试别的吧。
I'll try another one!
Lucinda，天哪，总算有救了。
Lucinda, thank you!
快请进。
Coming,coming here.
Anthony还在吗？
Anthony's still there?
不在，他刚走。
No, he just left.
在争取民主和人权的斗争中，
I encourage you all to espouse the cause of democracy
我永远都是你们最坚实的后盾。
and defense of human rights.
连绵不断的内战，带走了太多太多无辜者的生命，
It is essential that we fulfill this
peacefully
我们必须把这无休止的纷争彻底抛进历史的垃圾桶。
without further loss of lives.
我谨代表全国民主联盟
We,
the National League for Democracy,
向你们保证，
've Come to ensure that you, the people,
你们的心声，将会被倾听。
can finally make your voice heard.
这边是俺们村，
There is our village.
对面是另一个村。
Opposite is another village.
现在没有硬块了吧。
No lumps.
- Missing some oats.    -还缺点燕麦
- No, a little salt.    -错，是缺点盐。
好了！
Here!
尝尝吧。
Taste me that.
看起来不错。
It looks good.
你娘殁了。她，走了。
Your mother died!
She's gone!
娘？
Mom?
Khin Kyi女士，
The funeral of Daw Khin Kyi,
伟大的国父昂山先生的遗孀，的葬礼
widow of the great national hero, Aung San,
非常隆重。
were sumptuous.
尽管当局强迫国家公务人员坚守岗位，
Despite the absence of officials, forced by the authorities
不得参与悼念活动，
to appear on their workplace,
这起葬礼仍成为军事当局上台以来最大规模的群体活动。
any event did equaled since the coup.
成十万人护送灵柩
At least 100,000 people have accompanied the remains
前往墓地。
To the grave...
又少了一个眼中钉。
A problem solved!
其他的也该上路了。
Let's get the others as soon as possible!
谢了。
Thank you.
你很孝顺。
You have been a very dutiful daughter.
你父亲可以含笑九泉了。
Your father would be proud.
现在该尽的孝也尽了
Now your duty is completed,
你可以放心回家了。
you must be understood to be eager to get home again.
什么时候收拾好了，
As soon as your pack are ready,
我就可以送你去机场。
you will be taken to the airport.
Nyunt将军，恐怕没这个必要吧。
that will not be necessary,General Nyunt.
我对自己的母亲尽过孝了，现在是为祖国母亲尽孝的时候了。
For the time being, my duty remains here in Burma.
选举就在眼前了。
for the campaign.
那你的孩子怎么办？
What about those young boys of yours?
他们离开母亲怎么行呢？
They will be missing with their mother.
选举越早，我就能越早与他们团聚。
The sooner we conduct elections,
the sooner I can rejoin them.
您回去后也催催奈温将军吧。
Perhaps on your return,you could ask General Ne Win to make hest.
她说她暂时不走。
She said she would not go.
一直要待到选举结束。
After the elections.
让她尝点厉害。
Apply more pressure on this woman.
不准在这非法集会。都给我回家。
This meeting is prohibited.
Go home!
准备！
All in a row!
再敢往前一步就开枪了。
I will not hesitate to shoot!
预备！
Ready!
他们来真的。
They do not pretend.
我们先忍忍，改天再来吧。
Wait till another day.
不，怕什么，不过是外强中干罢了。
No, do not pay attention to them.
我只管过去，看他们能把我怎么样。
We will continue peacefully.
你们先待在这。
Stay there first.
后退！这是命令！
Go home! That's an order!
再不站住我就开枪了。
If you are still not
I will open fire!
一……
One ..
二……
Two...
住手！带上兄弟们，我们走！
Stop!
Remember your men, we're leaving!
兄弟们撤！
Let's go!
赶快离开这。
You should go now.
开始！
Loans!
一……
One ..
二……
Two...
三！
Three!
这世界上有什么是比一个将军更危险的东西吗？
What is more dangerous than a general ?
两个将军。
Two generals.
那么，
Then,
就是你
it's you
威胁说要开枪吗?
Which have threatened to shoot?
是，首长。
Yes.
而你……
And you...
是你主动救了她，是吗？
You have taken the initiative to save it.True?
你们今天都有机会上一课。
You will all have the opportunity to learn
a good lesson.
你，
Your weapon.
把枪给我。
Give it to me.
拉下去。
Take him.
她父亲成了烈士，成了我们挥之不去的梦魇。
His father, the martyr,
was a constant threat to us.
如果再出现一个烈士，我们都受不了。
We can not afford a second martyr.
不要莽撞行事。
Do not misunderstand me.
无本之木活不了多久，
The tree whose roots have been cut
她蹦跶不了几天了。
eventually fall alone.
面对威权政府变本加厉的恫吓，
In an unprecedented escalation intimidation,
昨日的一场集会中，
Aung San Suu Kyi
almost got shot by soldiers yesterday
昂山素季，差点被军人杀害。
while a rally in Danyubu province.
愿主保佑你，Suu！
Jesus Christ, Suu!
在争取民主和人权的斗争中，
I encourage you all to espouse the cause of democracy
我永远都是你们最坚实的后盾。
and defense of human rights.
连绵不断的内战，带走了太多太多无辜者的生命，
It is essential that us to fulfill this peacefully,
我们必须把这无休止的纷争彻底抛进历史的垃圾桶。
without further loss of lives.
民主万岁！
Democracy!
跟我走一趟！
Follow us!
不错的一天。
A good day today.
你呢，
Do not you, U Win Tin?
昂山女士，我们每去一个地方，
Daw Suu, everywhere we went,
他们就在那随便抓人。
they were arrested and taken people.
他们都被抓到什么地方了？
where were they taking?
有的被抓去边境劳改
Some in a forced labor camp at the border
为狗官们
to transport weapons and drugs
走私武器毒品。
for the generals.
其他人呢？
And the others?
我们应该给联合国和大赦国际写信，
We should write to the UN
告诉他们，
and Amnesty International to inform them
缅甸人遭受到何等非人的虐待。
to tell them exactly how the bumese people are being treated
by the military.
取纸来。
Hand me the paper, please.
8个月后
8 mouths later
亲爱的，
My darling,
为了维护他们摇摇欲坠的统治，
Every day new atrocities
地狱的种种天天在这里上演。
Committed by a regime
desperate to cling to power.
但你不能回来。
But you can not go back.
正如父亲所说，
As my father said:
"Continue to expect the best
做最好的准备，同时做最坏的打算。
while preparing for the worst. "
所以亲爱的，我请求你尽量别去担心。
So, darling, please,I beg you,try ur best not to worry.
爹。
Hi, Dad.
你妈问你好。
Your mother sends you love.
她怎么样?
How is she?
还是很忙。
Still busy.
我希望终有一天她能得到应有的回报。
I hope that his efforts will be rewarded.
你好
Hello.
- Please.     -请。
- Thank you.  -谢谢。
Finnis教授，
Professor Finnis.
抱歉。
Forgive me, forgive me.
很抱歉打扰您，我是Michael Aris教授，
Sorry to trouble you .
My name is Doc. Michael Aris,
昂山素季的丈夫。
I'm marrid to Aung San Suu...
久仰。
Of course!
你妻子的成就引人注目。
I like to watch your wife's progress
with admiration.
很抱歉打扰您。
Sorry to trouble you,
我猜您对诺贝尔和平奖评选委员会有一定影响力。
I think you have some influence
with the Nobel Peace Prize Committee.
您能帮她提名吗？
I was wandering if you be willing to forward her name?
她绝对够资格。
His candidacy is very solid.
任何提高她国际声誉的东西
Anything that reinforces its international reputation
都能对她提供一定的保护。
contributes in some way to protect.
您应该理解，
You can imagine,
the question of its safety
她的安全对我来说胜过一切。
weigh myself a lot.
你有她的简历吗？
DO u have some kind of CV
我可以向诺贝尔委员会递交申请。
I will present to Vaclav Havel and his Committee.
您帮了我一个大忙。
It would we very helpful.
您知道吗？
You see,
每一天我都在担心，运气会悄悄溜走。
everyday I tell myself that luck could abandon.
我尽力吧。
I will do my best.
感激不尽。
Thank you very much.
Karma，我正找你呢，跟我来。
Karma! I was looking for you.
Follow me.
Aris教授，我还得……
Dr Aris, I must...
我需要你的帮助
I need you.
我制定了一份行动计划，
Instead of sitting down and worry about the election date,
而不是坐在这守株待兔。
I concocted a plan of action.
I have here somewhere
这里有些昂山素季的资料。
all dissertations Suu .
包括介绍她父亲的
Including one of his father
以及缅甸殖民时代的一些资料。
and on colonial Burma.
你整理一下看能不能找出点什么。
Read all of this
and see what you can get.
我们要为昂山素季申报诺贝尔和平奖。
We will nominate Suu
the Nobel Prize.
给力。
It's great.
确实给力。
Yes.
快开始吧，让我们拭目以待。
Good. You can start!
We'll see what happens.
好兄弟。
Good man.
可能用处不大，但我还是要尽我所能来保护你。
It will not help
I tell you to preserve you,
时刻保持谨慎，
but please,
remains judicious in all things.
你必须选好时机。
You have to choose the right time.
因为深深地爱着你，
If your husband loves you deeply
still has some authority over you,
我冒昧地认为自己有权要求你这么做。
so listen to me, I pray.
像我爱你那样爱自己好吗？
Be as gentle with  yourself
as I would if I was there.
爹！
Dad!
一惊一乍地，一点都不稳重！
Warning!
天哪！
Oh goodness!
我们可以提前过年了。
Looks like the Christmas comes early.
Kim，轻点。
Kim, watch out, finally!
是哦，看你多完美啊！
Yes, my brother in perfect!
是。
Yes.
什么？
What?
怎么会！
Oh no!
好。
Yes.
对不住。
I'm sorry.
一会再打给你。
Lucinda, I will call you later.
好。再见。
OK. Goodbye.
爹？
Dad?
是Lucinda阿姨。
That was your Aunt Lucinda.
很不幸，你们的爷爷走了。
I'm sorry to have to tell u
your grandfather died.
我得回苏格兰去主持葬礼。
I have to go to Scotland to organize the funeral.
被提名诺贝尔和平奖的缅甸人
Burmese tipped for Peace Prize
大家都听着，
I'll tell you.
我们必须切断这个女人的一切外部联系，
This woman must be isolated
不管是国内，
all those who support it.
还是国外。
As to isolate the world...
首长？
Head?
属下倒有一计不知当讲不当讲。
I have an idea on the issue.
说吧。
Continue.
只要让我全权负责，
Give me the reins.
其它的事首长就不用担心了。
I can make it be forgotten,
here and elsewhere.
说个数字。
Tell a figure.
5。
（注：吴奈温极为迷信，有很强烈的数字崇拜情结）
5.
你先下去吧。
Sein Lwin , you may have.
现在，
Now
你直接对我负责，
you alone make me accountable.
这件事就完全交给你了。
You have carte blanche
to solve this problem.
- Count Me In.   -您就瞧好吧。
- Good.          -等你的好消息。
起床了！
Good morning!
太阳都晒屁股了。
It's time to wake up.
起床了！
Good morning!
睡醒了吗？
Sleep well?
孩子，
Now
别怕。
I do not want u to be frightened,
今天一大早，这帮土匪就搅扰了我们的清梦
but this morning we have wake woken to find the
house is surrounded by soldiers.
有可能什么都不会发生，
There is perhaps nothing will.
但万一我被抓走了，
But in case I am arrested, I
arranged
我会争取让你们遣返回国。
for your repatriation.
我向你们保证，无论发生什么，
I want you to know that whatever happens,
都会有人好好照顾你们的，好吗？
you will be well taken care of. Alright?
好吧。
Yes.
昂山素季，你被逮捕了。
Aung San Suu Kyi, you are officially
除了你的孩子，
Arrest. Apart from your children,
其他人通通离开。
everyone must leave.
都回去吧，路上一定要小心。
Enter quickly at home,
as discreetly as possible.
快走！
Out!
快！
Go away!
那些，通通带走。
Take that!
文件。
File.
快。
Immediately.
通通带走，不要留下一份文件。
Take everything.
Not allow any document here.
书也通通带走。
Drain the library.
我们逗你玩呢。
These are my jokes.
只不过好像没怎么把你逗乐。
They do not make you laugh, that's it.
带着妹妹去找你爹，快去。
Take the small and will find your father.
Go, dark!
文件通通带走。
Take all folders.
好吧。
Yes, I understand.
缅甸是切断了全国所有的电话，还是只切断了这一部？
But all the lines are cut in Burmese,
or just this one?
I see，just this one.
好，就这一部。
谢了
Thank you.
lnsein——缅甸最大监狱
lnsein:the largest prison in Burma
停，过来跟着我。
Hi,stop.Follow me!
你在仰光期间，
While you're in Rangoon,
也得遵守
you are to abide bide conditions
我们对你妻子的禁令
under which your wife has been detained.
不得接触外国使领馆
No contact with the Embassy
以及任何政治活动分子。
Nor any person engaged in politics.
都清楚了吗？
Is that understood?
清楚。
Yes.
享受这儿的一切吧。
Enjoy your stay!
想吃巧克力吗？可惜我们没有。
Chocolate? We don't have it.
孩子们！
Boys!
爹？
Dad?
其他人呢？
Where are the others?
俺娘绝食了，正躺着呢。
Mom in on hunger strike.
绝食？
On hunger strike?
他爹。
Mikey.
他们一大早过来抓走好多人
They came early in the morning and arrested
my colleagues,
我却还被软禁在这。
but I am under house arrest.
除非我也被抓进监狱，
I know that I will not eat
不然我就绝食到底。
until I put in prison too.
- They cut the phone line.   -他们断了电话。
- With scissors!        -剪掉了。
你难以想象
You can not imagine
你能来我有多高兴。
my relief that you're here.
你最后一次是什么时候吃的饭？
When did you last eat?
三天前吧。
About three days ago.
- Four.     -是四天。
- Three.    -是三天。
家里从没这么沉闷过。
It is never a dull moment in this family.
我能做点什么吗？
What do I do with you?
全世界都在担心
Fears are growing
英国科学家Aris教授的安危。
about the fate of Professor Aris, a British academic
两周前，
disappeared there for a fortnight.
他去仰光探望自己的妻子昂山素季，
It has not been seen since his arrival in
Rangoon
从那以后就再也没有人见过他。
to visit his wife Aung San Suu Kyi.
尽管政府数次向缅甸当局表示严重关切，
The Department has called for new
urgently
但缅甸当局始终拒绝回答
but the Burmese authorities refuse to say
他的行踪及安危。
if he's okay and where he is.
据英国大使馆透露，我们现在仅仅知道……
According to the British Embassy, ​​
the only thing we know is that...
娃他娘，
Listen, Suu.
如果你不在了，
If you die,
孩子们就没了娘，
the boys lose their mother
这片土地上的人民也会没了最后的希望。
and your people,their best defender.
我能做点什么吗？
Can I try something?
什么？
What?
乖乖坐下。
Sit.
起立。
Standing.
我有话要说。
I wish put a proposition.
我妻子绝食
It's been 12 days
已经12天了。
since my wife has not eaten anything.
我不得不告诉你们
I must tell you
她的身体状况有多么糟糕。
how vey rapidly her hearlth is decline.
她可以
She is prepared
放弃绝食，
to abondon her hunger strike,
只要你们能够保证
if you will offer her a formal assurance
给予她的同仁以人道待遇。
that her colleagues will be well treated.
她生命的垂危程度已经无法用语言形容，
I cannot emphasize the great danger she is.
最多还能挺一两天。
She will not survive more than a day or two.
我提醒你们注意
I ask you to consider very carefully
拖下去的严重后果。
the public consequences if you failed to act quickly.
夫人，政府向您保证
Authorities give you the assurance
不伤害您的同事。
no harm to your colleagues.
可以了吗？
All right?
昂山素季很关心你的安危嘛，
Aung San Suu Kyi is worried about you, apparently.
乖，吃得白白胖胖的啊。
Here, eat.
什么声音。
What is that noise?
这就是传说中的
It's called...
音乐。
Music.
长这么大以来，就这周过得最极品了。
I spent the week
the strangest of my life.
这几天多谢了。
Thank you for everything.
没有你我挺不过这段日子
I could not get this through without you.
你走了，这里又要空荡荡的了。
The house will be quiet.
无论你在哪里，
I know. I will continue
我都只离你一个转身的距离，
waving the red rag.
我会一直支持着你，直到我们看到胜利的曙光。
So long as we quickly tunnel.
我一定会好好的，Mikey。别担心。
I'm okay, Mikey. Do not worry.
照顾好孩子们。
Ta priority, it is boys.
我懂的。
I know.
缅甸政府正式宣布于五月进行全民公投。
The Burmese authorities have announced that the
ballot would be held in May.
遗憾的是，依据一条不起眼的法律，
However, Aung San Suu Kyi
was not authorized
如果配偶为外籍人士，
to be a candidate in elections
就不得竞选缅甸总统，
under an obscure law
所以昂山素季被禁止参选。
prohibiting the President of Burma
to have a foreign spouse.
明白。
I understand.
就这样吧。
Okay.
拜拜。
Bye.
- What call brutal!   -去他妈的。
- Who was that?       -谁啊。
大使馆。
The Embassy.
他们说孩子们不再符合条件，
Boys
no longer meet the conditions of Burmese nationality.
所以他们的护照要被取消了。
Their passports are invalidated .
难以置信。
It is beyond comprehension.
他们觉得把昂山素季和孩子们分开
They decided that preventing Suu
to see her children
就能让她知难而退。
was an effective way of breaking it.
至少他们答应公投了，
At least they hold elections.
让我们拭目以待，
Wait and see.
希望一切都能好起来。
Hopefully everything is resolved soon.
但愿吧。
Yes, hope.
我们唯一无法被剥夺的就是我们的希望。
We all cling to hope.
对缅甸民众来说，这曾经是难以置信的，
This is a day that few people in Burma ever imagined
无法想象这居然可以在这个国家成为现实
Across the country,
incredible scenes.
数千民众在四十多年来的第一次选举中
We press their thousands to vote
踊跃投票
first elections in 40 years.
据初步统计，
The first estimates are falling...
昂山素季
Aung San Suu Kyi
获得392票
392 seats.
军事当局，
The Burma military
10票。
10 seats.
她赢了！
She won!
谢天谢地！
Oh my God!
太棒了。
It's great!
缅甸全国上下
In Burma ,
掀起了一场昂山素季风潮。
it's a tidal wave extraordinary
for Aung San Suu Kyi
她所在的党派，
and her party, the National League
全国民主联盟也随之成为焦点。
for Democracy.
在一个禁止超过5人以上聚集的国家，
In a country where
gatherings of more than 5 persons are prohibited,
很显然，全民盟
NLD party seems
要为其胜利而狂欢了。
to celebrate his victory to the end of the night.
来，把花插上。
I'll put flowers in their hair.
公投最终结果
Final vote result
看，你们看！
Check this out!
那个疯婆子赢了。
This woman won.
混账！
This is absurd!
把电话给我！
Bring the phone!
站住！
Stop!
赶快给我回去！
Go back immediately!
说你呢，没听见吗？
Stop. Go back!
拜托不要这么幼稚好吗，我只是去和简单他们说几句。
Don't be silly. I just want to talk to them.
Do not be ridiculous.
- I'll talk to them.             -滚开。
- I have the authority to shoot. -你再敢前进一步我就开枪了。
有种你开。
You will not shoot.
给我回去！
Go back home!
请坐。
Take a sit.
公投已经结束，
Now that the elections were held,
我有好消息要告诉你。
I have good news for you.
当局想和你们达成共识,
Authorities are willing to find arrangement.
只要你写信给你妻子，
If you write to your wife
让她尽快回牛津
to encourage her to return to Oxford to live
faster,
他们可以准予你们早日团聚。
they will empower you from there.
知道了。
I see.
不过我认为完全没有必要
Since I have no intention
写这样一封信，
to ask such a thing to my wife,
所以我的回去了。
I'll take my leave.
这群狗杂种，
Those bastards will stop at nothing!
无法无天。
If they hope that I will flatten,
they will be surprised.
我们走。
Let's go.
尽管竞选失败，
Despite their crushing defeat,
缅甸军事当局仍然囚禁昂山素季
Burmese junta still do not release
Aung San Suu Kyi
使她无法在选举成功后顺利就任。
taking office as prime minister-elect.
她依然被软禁，
She is still confined  home
同时，她所在的党派——全民盟的
while leaders of his party, the NLD,
主要成员接连被捕。
are arrested one after the other.
由于僧侣发起抗议活动，
The monks launched a protest movement
目前众多寺庙被军管。
and monasteries were stormed by the army.
我向您保证，Aris教授
I assure you, Professor Aris
我们会尽全力，
we do our best.
不幸的是
However, we believe
对缅甸的经济制裁计划，
that by imposing economic sanctions against Burma
被敏感词否决。（自己意会吧）
with only plaint of hand of Beijing
他们利用这次机会来加强自己
They will seize this opportunity to tighten their economic stranglehold
对缅甸政府的影响力。
on Rangoon.
我还有个重要会议，
Now forgive me I have an important meeting to geet to,
祝您好运。
and I wish you all the best of luck,sir.
Finnis教授。
Pr Finnis.
- How are you?        -最近怎么样？
- I've been better.   -马马虎虎。
我猜你听完我说的就不是马马虎虎了。
I think what I have to say
will cheer you up.
我和孩子们此刻的喜悦与自豪中
The joy and pride I and my children feel this moments,
还夹杂着一丝悲伤和担忧。
are tinged with sadness and apprehension.
我不知道是否曾经有过这样被
I'm not sure if the Nobel Peace Prize has ever been given to
严密监禁的诺贝尔和平奖获得者。
someone in the situation of such extreme isolation before.
我只知道从来没有过如此的女性获得者。
And I know he was never given to
a woman in this situation.
由于政治上的原因，
This will do three years that Suu
is detained for political reasons
她一直都被军事当局软禁。
by the military regime.
即使作为她的家人，我们也毫无她的音信。
We, her family,
have no contact with her.
除了她很孤独外，
The only thing we know,
我们一无所知。
is that she's all alone.
出于私心，
I hope selfishly
我对经济上的改善也感到高兴，
that our situation will become more liveable
至少会让家庭状况好很多，
as the result of this supreme conditions
这也算是对她身心伤害的补偿吧。
for her moral and physical courage,
同时希望我们得到探望她的机会。
And that we will finally have the right to report
visit again.
我和孩子们都很想她。
We miss her very much.
我也想你们。
I miss you too.
我们中有一人得在颁奖仪式上发言
One of us will make a speech
at the award ceremony.
有谁想去吗？
Volunteers?
如果你娘可以收听广播的话，
If your mother has access to a radio,
能够听到你们的声音会让她深受鼓舞。
it will be very touched to hear
one of you.
我去。
I will.
好孩子。
Good. That's good.
挪威 1991
Norway 1991
We are in Oslo,the BBC World Service brings you the Nobel Price…
这里是奥斯陆，BBC在为您实时报导诺贝尔和平……
停电了。
There is no power!
连广播都听不了了。
We no longer have the radio!
没事，别担心，我去看看。
This is good, do not worry.
I'm on it.
有请Michael Alexander
I called Michael Alexander
以及Kim Aris
and Kim Aris
代表妻子
come forward to receive
the gold medal and diploma
以及母亲
on the behalf of your wife
上台领奖，
& your mother,
现在我宣布，1991年度
The Nobel Laureate
诺贝尔奖获得者，是——
昂山素季。
Aung San Suu Kyi.
幸好还有个收音机！
I have another radio!
快！快！
Quick, quick!
没电池了，等等。
Batteries are required, wait.
现在有请年轻的Alexander Aris，
Now it was the turn of the young Alexander Aris,
昂山素季的长子，
eldest son of Aung San Suu Kyi
上台演讲。
take place on the podium.
今天，我站在这
I stand here before you today
代表我的母亲——昂山素季
to accept on behalf of my mother,
Aung San Suu Kyi
接受最崇高的奖励——诺贝尔和平奖。
the best reward,
the Nobel Prize for Peace .
由于众所周知的原因她不能亲自前来，
Because circumstances prevented her from joining us,
只能由我在这里，尝试说出她的心声
I will try to say what she wants
probably express.
我们必须铭记，
We must remember that the lonely struggle
一个柔弱的女性，独自一人在重重监视之下不懈奋斗，
that takes place in a ownership
under surveillance in Rangoon
这是全世界人民
fits in the global fight
for Shipping
反抗暴政和一切真理部的斗争中，
of the human mind
一个小小的缩影。
of political tyranny and oppression psychological.
对历史的铭记，
Lessons from the past
will not be forgotten.
指引我们前进的方向。
but it's also for the future
我相信，我们的未来必将是一片光明。
that we celebrate today.
什么屌声音？
What is that noise?
这叫音乐。
From music.
这下老贼不得不退位了。
The old generals
will be forced to yield.
无非是时间长短而已。
This is a matter of time.
但愿如此。
Yes, I hope.
让我们拭目以待，
Let's see what happens.
看看他们还有没有别的伎俩。
Pathways military
are impenetrable.
你母亲肯定会为你而骄傲的。
Your mother would be very proud of you.
谢谢。
Thank you.
精彩！
Bravo.
No,no,no,no,no…
哦，你们不行
为什么不行？
Why not?
好吧，随你们好了。
Okay.
敬Suu。
Suu.
敬母亲。
Mom.
3年后
3 years later
把鞋脱了，别把泥带进屋。
Take off your shoes.
I do not want mud in the house.
晚饭七点半吃，Anthony叔叔要来。
The dinners later tonight, at 19:30.
Uncle Anthony is coming around.
怎么了？
What's wrong?
我想我娘了。
I miss Mom.
远离恐惧的自由
Freedom from fear
humanity must learn from Gandhi."——Martin Luther King,Jr.
"圣雄甘地指引我们前进的方向。"——马丁路德金
"To progress,
过去把他换下来。
Exchange with him.
艺术是思维的镜像。
"The art of a people
is a true mirror of their minds."
新来的吧？
Is it a new face?
你叫什么？
What is your name?
懂英语吗？
Can you speak English?
你叫什么名字？
So what is your name?
Arun。
Arun.
过来，给你看点东西。
Come here.
Let's me show you something.
我不吃人，别怕。
It's alright, I do not bite.
“你可以不关心政治，
"You may not think about politics.
但政治肯定会关心你。”
But the politics thinks of you. "
我父亲说的。
These are the words of my father.
你站那的时候可以想想。
Something for you to think about when you stand there.
你能抽出时间来见我，
Eminence , thank you
我荣幸之至。
take the time to receive me.
亲，我每天都会想起昂山素季。
Dear Michael, I think
Suu every day.
但愿我们能多做点什么。
I wish we could do more.
希望你能给我带来好消息。
I hope you bring me good news.
抱歉，不过情况还是几乎没变。
No, sorry,
but the situation has hardly changed.
那独夫民贼完全不理会
The fact is that the generals
scoff that the United States
美欧诸国的关切。
and Europe condemn their action.
没有某些亚洲国家的支持，
Asian Without support, I doubt
我很怀疑我们能否获得进展。
we make progress.
对不起我还有事。
Excuse me.
朋友们，
My Friends.
您好。
Hello!
耽误你们几分钟可以吗？
I want to annoy
few moments.
很高兴与您再会。
It is a pleasure to see you again.
东盟组织
The Asian Nations South East
对你们要求加入的申请
have carefully studied your request
进行磋商。
to join our association.
最终，
At the end of all,
决定接受你们成为我们中的一分子。
we are quite favorable.
很高兴听到这个消息。我们应该共同举杯庆祝这一好消息。
I am enchanted. We should made a toast!
然而虽然我们和美欧国家有一些冲突
But although the U.S. and Europe are our competitors,
我们还是不得不和他们保持良好关系。
we depend on their goodwill.
我们只是需要时间，
Democracy takes time to implement.
民主不是一夜建成的。
It is not done overnight.
我们理解。
We understand.
但你至少得做点样子出来。
It would be fashionable
you make a gesture.
还请不吝赐教。
What kind of gesture?
内政部长找您。
（相当于公安部，现任缅甸内政部长名字叫“哥哥”，
前段时间访华很是拉风）
The police chief is
here to see you.
您的监禁已经被正式解除。
Your house arrest is lifted.
从现在起，您可以自由行动了。
You are free to come and go as you please.
是你吗？真的是你吗？
Is that you?
你可能不会相信，但我现在确实是在英国大使馆给你打电话。
You will not believe it, but
I call the embassy.
我自由了。
I am free.
告诉孩子们，
Tell the boys
我自由了。
I am free.
难以置信！
I can't believe this!
我的同志们也都自由了。
ALL My colleagues also were released.
如果我快点，我明天……
If I hurry, I can succeed
明天就能见到你了。
to be with you tomorrow.
明天将是值得纪念的一天。
Tomorrow will be a big day.
多么令人期待的一天！
A wonderful day!
我想再开一次全民盟会议。
I hope to reorganize
a meeting of the NLD.
我人生中数一数二的幸运日。
One of the happiest days of my life.
最好明天早上我们就能见面
I hope we'll meet tomorrow morning.
我马上订票，最好是明天，
I'll call the airport .
It may be tomorrow.
尽可能快吧。
But very soon!
我们的斗争可以继续了
Because the fight goes on.
继续什么？
What goes on?
继续我们的斗争。
The fight goes on.
圣女——在等待
Lady in waiting
从没见过你如此活力四射
I've never seen her so radiant.
真高兴你们能来。
I'm glad you're here.
娘。
Hello, Mom.
Alexander!
当年的那个小孩子哪去了？
Where is my young boy?
能再次见到你们真是太高兴了。
So wonderful to see you again!
昂山女士，我们必须抓紧！
Daw Suu, we need to go!
很快回来。
I did not for long.
去吧。
Go.
爹。
Dad.
你在这！
There you are!
我到处找你。
I've been looking everywhere.
你懂的，不管你身在何处，
You know me.
我和你之间都只有一个转身的距离。
never very far.
多少次，我渴望着，能够再次就这样将你拥入怀中。
Many years ago I expected
hold you in my arms.
每当回想起你的种种
I can not stop pinching myself.
我都克制不住地掐自己。我止不住地去想你在做什么。
When I thought of you,
I imagined what you were doing.
我曾不止一次说过,
Often I told you,
Sometimes aloud.
你总是能让我安下心来,
You always make me reassured.
总是温暖着我，因为茫茫人海中，有一个人，这么深沉地爱着我。
You remembered me your unfailing love.
现在全世界都把你当作圣人。
You are aware that the world wants
beatify you.
可是我只是这大千世界中再平凡不过的一份子。
The cult of personality
does not interest me much.
圣人，不过是不懈奋斗的罪人罢了。
A saint, this is just a sinner who keeps on trying.
你还有什么缺点吗？
What are your faults?
你真忘了吗？
You forgot?
常常突然发怒，缺乏耐心。
My tantrums, my impatience.
还有，我一直都很固执。
And I am stubborn.
我都知道。
I know.
最近对你的赞美铺天盖地，
I've read good things about you,
anyway.
“女中曼德拉”“缅甸之星”
"The Female Mandela",
"The Star of Burma".
我最喜欢的一个是时代杂志上的，
My favorite is the one the Times.
在一张美丽的照片下面
A beautiful picture of you
写着“钢铁玫瑰”
and below,
the title "The Steel Orchid".
那你怎么看我？
How you see me?
站着你的面前，我的大脑就停止思考了。
Well,seeing you,I did not see much,
recently.
如果你想要轻松的生活，
If you want your freedom back...
尽管去过。
Just start it again...
如果你要这么做，
I want you to know
我会理解的。
I understand that.
听着。
Look.
我承认，长期分离很痛苦。
I will not deny that this long separation
is heavy.
不只是我，孩子们也是。
For boys, too.
但我也想申明一点，
But I want to make something perfectly clearly.
从一开始，
Since the beginning, against all odds
我们就胸怀同样的梦想——一个富强民主文明的新缅甸，
we have always shared the same dream
for Burma.
我认为这并不是什么障碍，
I consider him, not as an obstacle,
反而是我们之间最坚实的纽带。
but as the bond that unites us.
有夫如此，夫复何求。
You must be the husband
the most indulgent of all history.
1998年11月
November 1998
那是我最后一次见她。
That's the last time I saw her.
从那以后，就只能靠不断摩挲这张照片，
来寄托我无尽的思念。
Since that day,been wiped
refued one after another
赶快填好这些表格，我就能休息了。
I could fill out their forms
eyes closed.
- Thank you.   -谢谢。
- Nothing.     -客气了。
她知道了吗？
Suu know?
不管怎么说，
Finally,
你还是得告诉她。
you will have to tell her.
再等等吧。
All in good time, Anthony.
你到底准备怎么给她说？
How will you tell her?
英国来信！
A letter from England!
哦，是你啊，太好了。
How wonderful!
到最后，还能听到你的声音。
It does me good to hear your voice.
亲爱的，你现在怎么样？
How are you, darling?
你看过信了?
Did you get my letter.
我还是不敢相信。
I'm still trying to take it in.
天意如此。
Yes, of course.
不过，好消息是
The good news
为了我们的梦想，我一直战斗到了最后一刻。
is that I fully intended to fight all the way.
我最后只想再见你一面，
And nothing will stimulate me more than
coming see you.
如果签证顺利，
If all goes well for my visa...
而且
And I believe
上苍保佑我的身体条件允许，
that my condition would make them indulgent
我们可以，最后一次地，
once and for all...
一起为我过个生日。
We have a good chance to see us
for my birthday.
我们可得好好庆祝下，好吗？
We could celebrate together.
一定。
Right.
Yes.
老婆，高兴点。
Courage, Suu.
为了我高兴点好吗？
Courage. High hearts!
还在听吗？
Hello? Are you still there?
我在这呢。
Yes, I'm here.
好。
Good.
我以前的一个学生，
A former student of mine,
曾经做过和尚的
a former monk
Karma，
named Karma,
经常来照顾我。
is great to comfort me.
不错。
Good.
是啊。
Yes.
照顾好自己。
Take care of yourself.
马上就能再见面了。
See you soon. It will not be long.
娃他娘？
Suu?
Gordon先生，
Gordon, we...
Gordon,
我们必须向当局施压，
we must
try to pressure the authorities.
Anthony说，我们已经采取一系列行动。
According to Anthony
steps have already been undertaken.
他已经联系过Desmond Tutu（1984年诺贝尔和平奖得主）
和白宫方面，
He spoke to Desmond Tutu and the White House.
在Michael拿到签证以前，
Rest assured that none of us will sit
我们不会放弃哪怕一丝努力。
before Michael had his visa.
谢谢你们。
Thank you.
你怎么这么不爱惜身体。
You are your worst enemy.
我求你了，Michael，上床休息好吗？
I beg you, Michael.
Back to bed.
- It's almost midnight.   -都半夜了。
- I know.                 -我知道。
就10分钟，再给我10分钟好吗?
10 minutes, Karma.
Give me another 10 minutes.
我还得应付成堆
I have a mountain of alien's corresponse
的回信。
to treat.
时间不等人。
It can not wait.
我走了，学生们怎么办？
Who will care for my students?
他们都还指望着我呢。
There are people who count on me.
我不能躺在床上虚度生命。
I can not spend my time hanging out in bed.
求你了……
Please...
再忙上10分钟我一定睡觉。
I'll go to bed in 10 minutes.
你保证？
Promised?
我保证。
I promise.
明天见。
Tomorrow.
晚安。
Good night.
你那一切都好吗？
How are you?
你听说什么了吗？
Have you heard of anything yet?
尽量快点，他们一会又要切断电话了。
Quickly, before they cut the line.
我只想知道
I need to know.
大夫允许你长途奔波吗？
Do they
suggested that you could come?
当然了，随便哪一天都行。
Any day now.
我向你保证，
I promise you.
不会太久。
It will not be very long.
我想……
I thought...
什么？
What?
我……
Should I...
你觉得我该不该过来找你？
do you think I should come to see you?
千万别这样，想也别想。
You must not think about it for a moment.
现在是最紧要的关头，
It was not all that to collapse so close.
绝大多数人都支持我们，
The highest level support us.
这一切都……
Everything suggests that...
什么？
What?
爹。
Hi.
是你娘。
It was your mother.
她让我带问你好。
She kisses you.
虽然有点晚，
It took longer than expected.
但我早就知道
But I knew
即使是昂山将军的女儿，
someday
even the daughter of General Aung San
最终也不得不放弃。
eventually give up.
夫人。
Madam.
将军仔细考虑了您的请求，
General
has read your letter carefully.
他让我来通知您，
He asked me to inform you
很不幸，当局没有可以在途中
that the authorities simply do not have the resource
照顾您先生的相关设备。
to deal with your husband's medical needs.
你们的好意我领了，但这不用你们担心。
It's not what you are asked.
挪威政府借给我们一架备有医疗器械的直升机，
The Norwegian government
lends us an air ambulance.
敏感词派他的医生在一路上照顾Michael。
The Dalai Lama sends us
one of his doctors to follow Michael.
当然，出于人道主义考虑，
You want to be with your husband
in such a time.
我可以为您安排下一航班，
I offer you a place
on the next flight.
这样，你们明天就能团聚了。
You might be at his bedside
tomorrow.
你们这是想赶我走。
You would not let me go back.
您可以自由选择，
You are free to choose,
是您的家人
between your husband and your children
还是祖国。
and your country.
这是何等的自由！
What kind of ​​freedom is that?
签证被拒
Visa rejected
又一次被拒了。
Another refusal.
可是，我再也等不起了。
And meanwhile
time slips through my fingers.
我甚至都没有准备好离开。
I am not ready to go yet.
在听吗？
Do you hear me?
我多么想变的像Kim
I want to become of Kim
和Alex他们这么大啊。
and Alex?
Michael，深呼吸。
Michael, take a deep breath.
我觉得好像快要失去意识了。
I feel like I lose my mind.
冷静。
Calm yourself.
爹，
Dad.
很抱歉
I'm sorry.
屋漏偏遭连阴雨，这是要我的老命啊。
It makes me sick to be sick.
您是？
Who are you?
夫人，我是新来的保姆。
The housemaid, ma'am.
我想和我丈夫说几句。
I want to talk to my husband.
他昨晚病得很重，现在还在医院休养。
He had a very bad night.
It is Palliative Care.
他们留下了他朋友Karma的手机号。
They left
number of his friend Karma.
你需要他的号吗？
I give you?
好。
Yes. Please.
是Karma吗?
Karma?
夫人，很抱歉，您丈夫现在在接收临终特护。
（注：hospice是国外一种为垂死病人提供全面照顾的服务）
The news is not good.
Michael is in the hospice now.
病情急速恶化。
It declines quickly.
应该还有办法的。
We must do something.
It must be possible.
他们已经用尽所有办法了。
They tried everything.
很抱歉。
I'm sorry.
娘。
Hi, Mom.
他的时间所剩不多了。
It did not for long.
我接受不了。
But I can not.
我还被困在这。对不起。
My hands are tied.I'm sorry.
我知道。
I know.
他已经奄奄一息了。
He's dying.
我知道你很难过。
Please, try to understand.
这也是我和你父亲
It would be an end
这么多年来共同奋斗的一个终结。
of everything your father and I fought for so long.
我娘问候您。
Mom sends her love.
1999年3月
March 1999
明天就是我生日了。
It's my birthday tomorrow, you know.
是，我知道。
Yes, I know.
老天爷差不多
Fitting time
也要收我而去了。
moment to my final bow, I think.
诺贝尔和平奖获得者昂山素季的丈夫
The husband  Nobel Peace Prize winner
Aung San Suu Kyi
在度过自己53岁生日的时候撒手人寰……
has died of cancer
on his 53rd birthday...
8年后
8 years later
2007年 仰光
Rangoon 2007
昂山素季！昂山素季！
Aung San Suu Kyi!
昂山素季被软禁15年后，于2010年被释放。
然而，根据国际特赦组织，缅甸军政府继续
保持骇人听闻的人权纪录。它被指控与多起
人口失踪，包括儿童失踪，屠杀，酷刑，强
奸和强迫劳动有关。直至今日，全国范围内
还有2100名政治犯，其中包括17个记者。这
部电影的成功拍摄有赖于他们的同事的帮助。
--  The End  --
"Please use your liberty to promote ours."——Aung San Suu Kyi
请用你们的自由帮助我们的自由——昂山素季